Mehdi Mahmud

- → Full-Stack Web Developer
- → Scientific Researcher

- n 15, Century way, Birmingham, B63 2TQ
- +44(0)7511118806
- mehdi.mahmud@hotmail.com
- in https://www.linkedin.com/in/mehdi-mahmud/



https://mehdimahmud79.github.io/portfolio/



https://github.com/MehdiMahmud79

ABOUT ME **OBJECTIVES**

Full-stack web developer and scientific researcher with a passion for coding and problem solving situated in Birmingham. As a skilled programmer, I can adapt to all stages of advanced programming. I am confident in my technical skills which range from coding and user interface to testing and debugging procedures. I hold a PhD in Applied Mathematics from the University of Birmingham and since 2000 I have gained experience in several different domains which include academic research, lecturing, IT, and professional video editing. More recently, I completed an intense Full-Stack Web Developer Bootcamp at the University of Birmingham, which I completed in November 2021 having obtained an overall grade of A+.

I look forward to offering my skills as a Full Stack web developer in the future as part of a fast-paced yet quality-driven team.

SKILLS

Web Languages / Technologies used:

JavaScript, Express.Js, Node.Js, React, CSS, HTML, Tailwind, Bootstraps, MySQL, MongoDb, Sequelize, Jest, Apollo Server, JWT, GitHub

Other Languages and Software

Fortran, Matlab, Visual Basic, Adobe Premiere, Microsoft Office, 3d Software (Abagus).

Personal Skills

- Confident in leading a department, teaching and working in a team.
- High level of coding and technical literacy.
- Years of experience in problem solving and logic.
- Advanced Mathematical and IT knowledge.
- Adaptable to different work environments.
- Open to learning and expanding knowledge.
- Diligent and successful in completing and multitasking long-term projects.
- Strong communicative and organizational skills.
- Strong work-ethic and punctuality.

PROJECTS |

Find all of my projects at: https://mehdimahmud79.github.io/portfolio/

InQuizitive

Senior Developer (Developing the BackEnd and Manage the FrontEnd React Framework)

MovieTime

Senior Developer (Developing the BackEnd and fixing the Problems in the FrontEnd)

HolidayPlanner

Developer (WebPageStyling using tailwind and Api requests).

EDUCATION

Bootcamp Certificate | May2021-Nov2021 Full Stack web Development | University of Birmingham

Gained proficiency in front end and back end technologies through a dynamic full stack curriculum, including HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, jQuery, Bootstrap, Express.js, React.js, Node.js, Database Theory, MongoDB, MySQL, Git,

PhD. | Oct 2015-Jul 2020 Applied Mathematics | University of Birmingham

Developed a software to simulate Bubble Dynamics using parallel programming in Fortran language.

"MICROBUBBLE DYNAMICS NEAR RIGID BOUNDARIES"

Msc. | Oct 2007 – Jul 2009 Computational Mathematics | Salahaddin University-Erbil

Developed a software to solve some types of integral equations using Matlab.

"APPROXIMATION METHODS ON SOLVING A SYSTEM OF LINEAR 2D FREDHOLM INTEGRAL EQUATIONS"

BSc. | Oct 1998 - Jul 2002 General Mathematics | Salahaddin University-Erbil

Produced a multi-language application using *Visual Basic* to secure text documents using some advanced cipher systems.

"USING PRIMITIVE POLYNOMIALS IN BLOCK CIPHER TO CREATE A SECURE APP USING VISUAL BASIC"

EXPERIENCE

➤ Research Fellow | SEP 2019 - MAY 2021

University of Birmingham

In collaboration with the School of Dentistry, my main pieces of research involved improving the cavitation around ultrasonic dental scalers.

- Using ABAQUS and the finite element approach to conduct a numerical study for an ultrasonic dental scaler
- Developing a novel mathematical model to calculate the amount of cavitation near a dental implant. This model is now being used as a method of improving dental cleaning techniques
- Participating in teamwork by performing experiments in a lab environment. The lab results were used to compare and validate computational results
- Publishing an academic paper in Jove Scientific Journal

➤ Teaching Assistant | JAN 2015 - DEC 2019

University of Birmingham

During my Ph.D. study in the school of Mathematics, I worked as a part-time teaching assistant.

- Assisting undergraduate students in their educational endeavours
- Developing their knowledge of several different mathematical fields: **Numerical Analysis, Computational Mathematics using Maple, Mathematical Biology, C++ programming, and logic**).
- Keeping up-to-date with upcoming topics so that I was able to answer any of the students' queries.
- Grading work and providing feedback
- Invigilating examinations

➤ Lecturer and Undergraduate Administrator | SEP 2009 - SEP 2014

University of Salahaddin-Erbil

Full-Time Assistant lecturer at Mathematics Department / College of Science to teach (Introduction to Cryptography, Matlab, Visual Basic, Advanced Calculus, Computational Mathematics, Numerical Analysis).

As a Lecturer and Undergraduate Administrator, my role was to

- Organize timetables and examinations
- Provide lectures, educational resources, and advice for undergraduates
- Supervising final year students in their projects
- Building staff-student rapport

During my time at the university, I briefly took on the position of the Head of School for six months. This role allowed me to:

- Develop a firm understanding of the needs of both staff and students by offering advice, holding meetings, and solving any issues.
- Mediating inquiries between students and members of staff
- Manage and distribute financial resources
- Communicate with other schools within the University to organize research collaborations and conferences.
- Be an active member of the examination committee for the College of Science.

➤ Teaching Assistant | Jan 2003 - Sep 2007

University of Salahaddin-Erbil

As a Full-Time Teaching Assistant at the Mathematics Department, my roles included

- Teaching students in the following fields of mathematics and computing: Computer programming using visual Basic, advanced calculus, Computational Mathematics using Matlab, Cryptography systems, Latex Package
- Providing support to students during their academic endeavours by providing them with resources and advice
- Researching and applying different teaching techniques to communicate mathematical concepts effectively to different learning types.

Due to my background in computational skills, I was selected as a member of the Examination Committee whilst also being a Teaching Assistant. This role included

- Data entry
- Creating a data-base of results
- Preparing results certificates.

➤ IT and Video Editor | Jan 2000 - Dec 2014

During my time in Higher Education, I also worked as a part-time professional Video Editor for several different TV channels (Iraqia TV, Zagros Tv, and Gulan TV).

- As the head of the Graphics and IT Department, I taught my colleagues how to solve general as well as technical IT problems.
- Providing virtual lessons to the public on video editing and general IT knowledge
- Using Adobe Premiere Pro and Avid NewsCutter to edit and dub news reports, TV shows, and video clips.

TRAINING COURSES

- Academic Consultancy One Day Workshop, University of Birmingham Enterprise Limited, 29th May 2019.
- Software Carpentry Python, the workshop focused on Python and the curriculum will include: The Unix Shell,
 Version Control with Git, and Programming with Python, University of Birmingham, UK, 27th and 28th December 2018
- Mathematical Analysis of Incompressible Fluid Flows. A Sussex School and Workshop on the Navier-Stokes and Euler Equations. University of Sussex, Brighton, UK,18-22 September 2017.

Publications

- 1. Wang, Q., Mahmud, M., Cui, J., Smith, W.R. and Walmsley, A.D., 2020. Numerical investigation of bubble dynamics at a corner. *Physics of Fluids*, 32(5), p.053306.
- 2. Vyas, N., Mahmud, M., Wang, Q.X. and Walmsley, A.D., 2020. Imaging and Quantification of the Area of Fast-Moving Microbubbles Using a High-Speed Camera and Image Analysis. JoVE (Journal of Visualized Experiments), (163), p.e61509.
- 3. Rostam K. Saeed and Mehdi H. Mahmud, Solution of a system of two-dimensional linear Fredholm integral equations of the second kind by quadrature methods, Australian Journal of Basic and Applied Sciences, Vol.3, No.3 (2009), 1701-1715.
- 4. Mehdi H. Mahmud and Rostam K. Saeed, Numerical Solution of System of Two-DimensionalLinear Fredholm Integral Equations of the Second Kind by Adomian Decomposition Method, Proceeding of the 4th International scientific conference of Salahaddin University-Erbil, October 18-20, Vol.1 of 4 (2011), 31-34.fa

Research Interests

- Bubble dynamics; Modeling Cavitation
- Boundary integral method
- Numerical Modeling; Computational Fluid Dynamics.
- Abagus ; Modeling Cavitation around ultrasonic dental scaler.